Guide to the Stanford University, Engineering Case Program, Case Files SC0269
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Case studies
  - Development of a New Drill Steel at Ingersoll-Rand Company, H. O. Fuchs and Ronald J. Shuman, 1967; ECL 94; Total 20 pages, including text, drawings, material specifications, and a patent application.
    Rock drills are used in mining, in excavating, and in other applications where it is necessary to remove hard rock. The drills produce holes into which blasting charges are later inserted. These holes may be as shallow as a few feet or as deep as one hundred feet. Depths of fifty feet are common. The holes are produced by a bit which is attached to one end of the drill rod (or steel). A pneumatic hammer hits the other end of the drill steel, through a so-called shank piece. The drill steels themselves, each about ten feet long and one and a half inches in diameter, are threaded at both ends and joined by couplings. This case study provides some background on the drilling process and the characteristics of existing drill steels, then traces the development of an improved drill steel.
  - Development of an Undersea Power Supply at Aerojet General Corporation, William J. Clemens, 1967; ECL 96; Total 18 pages; 10 text and 8 exhibits.
    In March of 1967, Mr. Carl Carney of Aerojet General's Nucleonics Division in San Ramon, California, was completing plans for modifications to be included in the second prototype of Aerojet's Undersea Radioisotope Power Supply (URIPS). Mr. Carney had been working on the project since late 1965 and this prototype was scheduled to be the last design model in the URIPS series before production was started.
  - Pump Plunger Improvements at Kobe Inc., Robert Martin, 1969; ECL 100; Total 20 pages: 3 pages text, 17 pages exhibits
    Kobe Inc. manufactures a positive displacement type triplex pump which is used in their hydraulic oil well pumping system. To achieve reliability in these pumps, which must operate continuously at high pressures (up to 30,000 psi.), Kobe engineers must continually refine their design. As an example of such refinement, this case follows the development of the pump plunger and liner over a period of 24 years.
  - Development of a High Speed Weighing Machine at FMC, Sue Hays, 1969; ECL 109; Total 23 pages: 17 pages text, 6 pages exhibits.
    The overall design process is traced step-by-step from an original concept to the manufacture of several commercially useful prototypes. The designer was seeking a quantum improvement in a food-weighing device by using fluidics instead of electronics.
  - Hiller Aircraft Company II, (A) Design of a Supercharger Inlet Duct, (B) Filter Housing Clearance Considerations, (C) Structura Bracket Design, (D) Engine Shroud Design, P. Z. Bulkeley, H. O. Fuchs, E. J. Echterling, 1964; ECL 28; Total 42 pages (Parts A,B,C,D) with 14 text, 28 exhibits.
    The company has decided to install a supercharger on the model 12-E helicopter to give it higher altitude capability. The addition requires modification of an inlet duct. In the first of four subcases, the duct design is complete except for drawing the intersection of two pieces, a descriptive geometry problem. Paper cutout patterns are included to save students' time. In Part B, Bill Lancaster, a power plant engineer in the company has decided that clearance between the duct and part of the airframe should be checked, another descriptive geometry problem, requiring consideration of motion of the engine on its mounts as well. Part C presents the need for a simple structural bracket design. Part D presents the need for an engine shroud design, mainly a sketching problem.
  - Radiation Products Company, Failure of a Rotating Mirror, H. O. Fuchs, J. K. Williams, 1965; ECL 30; Total 28 pages, with 13 text, 15 exhibits.
    The company has been having problems with a mirror designed to rotate at speeds of around 10,000 revolutions per second for taking high-speed photographs. Attempts at solution over a period of years have not yet provided the answer and the question is what should be done next.
  - Precision Instrument Corporation, Experience with a Tape Reel Hold-down Mechanism, H. O. Fuchs, R. D. Regier, 1965; ECL 31; Total 26 pages, with 9 text, 17 exhibits.
    Company engineers are dissatisfied with existing hold-down knobs used in one of their tape recorders, feeling they are not simple or inexpensive enough. The case presents their viewpoints plus data on existing devices as background for student design projects.
  - William Wohlfort, Design of a Variable Frequency Oscillator, R. E. Miller, W. Wohlfort, 1965; ECL 35; Total 30 pages (Parts A,B,C,D) with 15 text, 15 exhibits.
    Electronic circuit design of a variable frequency oscillator is the focus of this case. Each of the first three sections ends with an unresolved problem answered by the professional in the start of the succeeding section.
  - Allied Solid Rocket Corporation, E. J. Fisher, 1965; ECL 37; Total 47 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 26 text, 21 exhibits.
    Need for expansion of a large and fairly complex facility for mixing solid rocket fuel has raised a variety of engineering problems which are presented in three sections of the case. The first concerns decision among three specific alternatives for general design of the expansion. The second concerns selection of a heat exchanger, and the third concerns selection of a pump to move the mix.
  - Dymo Industries, Inc., Design of a Tapewriter Component, H. O. Fuchs, J. A. Alic, 1965; ECL 38; Total 12 pages (Parts A,B) with 5 text, 7 exhibits.
    In the first of two parts a company engineer is asked to redesign a tape label dispenser so it can handle two different widths of tape. The second part then goes on to tell how he did the job. An instructor's note is available.
  - Rucker Company, (A) A Centrifuge Project, (B) Inertia Starter for the Centrifuge, (C) Centrifuge Clutch Design, H. O. Fuchs, O. Lorentsen, A. Krauter, 1965; ECL 39; Total 16 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 7 text, 9 exhibits.
    The design of a centrifuge is described in three installments, each ending with some unsolved problems. Suggested questions for the student appear at the end of each installment.
  - Hughes Tool Company, Aircraft Division, Development of a Light Observation Helicopter for the United States Army, K. H. Vesper, E. J. Echterling, 1965; ECL 41; Total 36 pages (Parts A,B) with 12 text, 24 exhibits.
    The first of two parts describes the need for sketching possible fuselage configurations for a new light observation helicopter. The second part tells how the craft was designed by the company to win competition for a large Army contract. A brief instructor's note presents a viewpoint regarding what can be learned from the experience.
  - Gar Wood Industries, Inc., Failures at Welded Joints in a Hopper Trailer, H. O. Fuchs, J. A. Alic, 1965; ECL 42; Total 27 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 11 text, 16 exhibits.
    In three installments this case tells of attempts by company engineers to eliminate some failures which are occurring in welded joints of a hopper trailer pulled by large diesel trucks.
  - Peterson Tractor Company, Design of a Side Sloper, H. O. Fuchs, J. A. Alic, Revised by Richard C. Bourne, 1965 1968; ECL 43; Total 30 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 13 text, 17 exhibits.
    An angled blade for a bulldozer needs to be drawn, confronting one of the company engineers with a problem in descriptive geometry. The first of three parts describes the problem situation and gives suggested questions for the student. The second consists of notes for the instructor, and the third tells what the company engineer actually did.
  - Dynasham Truck Company, Ltd., Truck Suspension Bolt and Bushing Failures, H. O. Fuchs, J. A. Alic, 1966; ECL 44; Total 37 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 13 text, 24 exhibits.
    Lance O'Leary, a young graduate engineer, is confronted with failure of a bolt and rubber bushing which connect a leaf spring to a truck frame. By repeated analyses of the failure, investigation of the part, and redesign, he succeeds in overcoming the problem. He also develops some designs which he would have used if the problem had not been solved by his earlier attempt. Lance's work in this case includes stress calculations, life test specifications, material selection, and consultation with various suppliers.
  - Marvetti, Inc., Design and Development of a Printing Calculator, H. O. Fuchs, J. A. Alic, 1966; ECL 45; Total 91 pages (Parts A,B,C,D,E) with 20 text, 71 exhibits.
    Part A gives the background of the company, the state-of-the-art of printing calculators, and organization chart of Marvetti, and a brief history of the management decisions before Harvey Shaw was assigned as Project Engineer. Part B discusses the extensive test programs used in the development of business machines. Part C shows some of the moves which were made in order to start production of this machine in a European plant of this American company. Part D shows a number of the design changes which were necessary to debug the machine after pilot production had been started.
  - Systron-Donner Corporation, Design of an Analog Computer, H.O. Fuchs, J.A. Alic, 1966; Case 47: (Box 2)
  - Travaglio Engineering Company, Manufacturing Design for a Cycle Timer, R.E. Keller, 1966; Case 51: (Box 2)
  - Development of a Dynamic Seal at Beckman Instruments, Inc.-Spinco Division, William J. Clemens, David Horine, 1967; Case 52: (Box 2)
  - Ford Motor Company, Design of an Automatic Welding Machine, J.A. Alic, 1968; Case 53: (Box 2)
  - Beckman and Whitley, Inc. II, Design of a Mirror Mount, H.O. Fuchs, D.A. Horing, Revised by Richard C. Bourne, 1966 1968; Case 54: (Box 2)
  - Dalmo Victor/Alic-Hayes, Case 56: (Box 2)
  - Lawrence Radiation Laboratory, an Ultra-High Vacuum Flange Seal, K.H. Vesper, J.A. Alic, 1966; Case 57: (Box 2)
  - Stanford Linear Accelerator Center I, (A) Development of a Remotely Operable High-Vacuum coupling, (B) The SLAC Design, (C) Ring-spring Analysis and Load Spring Design Problems, (D) Coil Spring Design, (E) Material Selection, (F) Ring-Spring Material Selection and Casting Problems, J.A. Alic, 1966; Case 59: (Box 2)
  - Art Whiting, To Weight A man in Space, K.H. Vesper, 1966; Case 60: (Box 2)
  - Philco Corporation I, (A) Satellite Tracking and Commanding Console Layout, (B) Student Console Layout Solution, (C) Panel Evaluation and Testing, R. H. McKim, J. K. Williams, 1965; ECL 25; Total 55 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 15 text, 40 exhibits.
    Is human factors engineering really just application of simple common sense or does it require special professional competence? Part A describes a test designed by the company to compare skills of professionals in this field with those of amateurs. Part B shows the performance of one of the amateurs. Part C presents further overall results of the test from which conclusions are to be drawn.
  - Stanford Linear Accelerator Center II, Beam Pipe Cooling System, J.A. Alic, 1966; Case 61: (Box 2)
  - General Electric Company, Vallecitos Atomic Laboratory, Ventilation Exhaust Stack, P.A. Bulkeley, D.A. Horine, Revised By Sue Hays, 1967; Case 62: (Box 2)
  - Data International II, Voltage Regulation, J. W. Hill, 1966; Case 63: (Box 2)
  - Data International III, Electrical Appliances, J.W. Hill, 1966; Case 64: (Box 2)
  - UTC/Dix-Short-Ewbank/1966 Summer Institute, Case 66: (Box 2)
  - Hewlett-Packard V, Microwave Switch, W.E. Bullock, J.W. Hill, G.R. Powley, 1966; Case 67: (Box 2)
  - Ampex Corporation, Tape Recorder Capstan Shaft, K.H. Vesper, J.A. Alic, 1966; Case 68: (Box 2)
  - City of San Jose-IBM Corporation Computerized Traffic Control, D.O. Covault, G.A. Fleischer, P.F. Williams, 1966; Case 69: (Box 2)
  - Bechtel Corporation, Process Analysis and Optimization of a Desalting Plant Design, J.W. McCutchan, R.P. Vail, E.N. Zeigler, 1966; Case 70: (Box 2)
  - Varian Associates, Redesign of a Liquid Nitrogen Container, William S. Chalk, Ivan A. Shirk and Robert B. Thornhill, 1967; Case 72: (Box 2)
  - Switching a Tracking Antenna, Sue Hays, 1968; Case 73: (Box 2)
  - Beckman and Whitley, Inc. I, Design of a 16mm Portable News Film Camera, H. O. Fuchs, D. A. Horine, Revised by Richard C. Bourne, 1966 1968; ECL 46; Total 34 pages, with 9 text, 25 exhibits.
    A leader in the field of scientific high-speed cameras enters the field of cameras for TV spot reporting. Progress of the project from the initial decision through early idea sketches and several prototypes to the successful production design is described in this case.
  - Systron-Donner Corporation, Design of an Analog Computer, H. O. Fuchs, J. A. Alic, 1966; ECL 47; Total 36 pages (Parts A,B) with 10 text, 26 exhibits.
    Dick Dunlop is charged with the overall design of a small analog computer from given components and subsystems. Part A gives the background of the company and of the product. Part B shows a number of Dick's early sketches and the finished product. It also discusses a detail mechanical problem connected with a latch mechanism.
  - Travaglio Engineering Company, Manufacturing Design for a Cycle Timer, R. E. Keller, 1966; ECL 51; Total 14 pages, with 9 text, 5 exhibits.
    Mr. Dalny Travaglio, consulting design engineer, had developed and tested the conceptual design for a high accuracy, high repeatability cycle timer. This case presents the information required for carrying out the final mechanical design of the timer and is intended as an exercise in design for mass manufacture.
  - Development of A Dynamic Seal at Beckman Instruments, Inc.-Spinco Division, William J. Clemens, David Horine, 1967; ECL 52; Total 14 pages, with 4 text, 10 exhibits.
    Mr. Chet Arnessen, a young employee of Beckman Instruments, was asked to redesign part of the buffer pump of his company's Model 130 Spectrochrom Analyzer. A few of Beckman's customers had complained that the moving seals in this pump developed leaks after very little use; these complaints were reaching the company at the rate of one or two a month with some repeats. Beckman's customers were scattered all over the world and, since the Spectrochrom Analyzer is not portable, the company had to send its Field Service personnel to them to make whatever repairs were necessary.
  - Ford Motor Company, Design of an Automatic Welding Machine, J. A. Alic, 1968; ECL 53; Total 25 pages; 9 drawings, 3 reproduced from Ford Motor Company originals, and 6 pages of other exhibits.
    Ray Rogers and Bill Fleming are assigned the problem of designing an automatic welding device to replace the manual spot welding of rocker panels on the Mustang. Part A outlines the problem. Part B shows the solution which, however, introduced a new problem: the machine interfered with the smooth flow of bodies along the production line. Part C shows how this difficulty was overcome.
  - Beckman and Whitley, Inc. II, Design of a Mirror Mount, H. O. Fuchs, D. A. Horine, Revised by Richard C. Bourne, 1966 1968; ECL 54; Total 12 pages (Parts A,B) with 5 text, 7 exhibits.
    Les Brown, who was in charge of the job said, We wasted a considerable amount of time due to the fact that we had all forgotten our descriptive geometry. The case concerns the determination and communication of the specifications for a block which fits into the camera and holds a mirror which reflects the light at 90 degrees to the side and 30 degrees upwards. The erroneous original sketches and the finished shop drawing with tolerances are shown beside the data necessary as background for this part. An instructor's note is available.
  - Lawrence Radiation Laboratory, An Ultra-High Vacuum Flange Seal, K. H. Vesper, J. A. Alic, 1966; ECL 57; Total 7 pages, with 4 text, 3 exhibits.
    While developing a new ultra-high vacuum seal needed for connecting pipes in nuclear fusion research equipment (Project Sherwood), Mr. Tom Batzer, a mechanical engineer, had to determine the size, spacing, and torque for flange bolts. A one page conclusion section describes how he approached the problem.
  - Stanford Linear Accelerator Center I, (A) Development of a Remotely Operable High-Vacuum Coupling, (B) The SLAC Design, (C) Ring-Spring Analysis and Load Spring Design Problems, (D) Coil Spring Design, (E) Material Selection, (F) Ring-Spring Material Selection and Casting Problems, J. A. Alic, 1966; ECL 59; Total 49 pages (Parts A,B,C,D,E,F) with 14 text, 35 exhibits.
    The six parts present the history of a remotely operable high-vacuum coupling design. The story presents problems in materials selection (including indium and stainless steel), elastic analysis and deflections, and design.
  - Art Whiting, To Weigh A Man In Space, K. H. Vesper, 1966; ECL 60; Total 15 pages, with 6 text, 9 exhibits.
    Intended for freshman orientation, this case dealing with design of a means to weigh a man in space has also been used successfully at graduate level. The analytic problem faced by Mr. Whiting at the end of the case is to determine the man's mass from Newton's second law from stopwatch experimental data. The question then is what to do about the fact that the accuracy is not quite satisfactory. Teaching objectives are similar to ECL 58, namely, to let the freshman see that his elementary science applies but he needs more to become a pro.
  - Stanford Linear Accelerator Center II, Beam Pipe Cooling System, J. A. Alic, 1966; ECL 61; Total 93 pages (Parts A,B,C,D,E) with 29 text, 64 exhibits.
    After general agreement had been reached that the pipe should be cooled by circulating liquid the question for SLAC mechanical engineer Al Lisin was, how? In five parts this case unfolds the history of the design. Intended primarily for use in a graduate-level heat transfer course.
  - General Electric Company, Vallecitos Atomic Laboratory, Ventilation Exhaust Stack, P. Z. Bulkeley, D. A. Horine, Revised by Sue Hays, 1967; ECL 62; Total 16 pages (Parts A,B,C,D) with 9 text, 7 exhibits.
    During extension of the ventilation stack one of the construction engineers noticed cracks in the concrete base. Mr. Don Brown, a mechanical engineer, undertook to analyze the problem and propose a solution. Four chapters describe how he proceeded with the analysis, in which he assumed that wind-induced vibrations caused the cracking.
  - Data International II, Voltage Regulation, J. W. Hill, 1966; ECL 63; Total 19 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 5 text, 14 exhibits.
    A practical case intended to interest students in the application of circuit analysis, presented in three parts. Need for an inexpensive method for reducing the fluctuation of the voltage supplied to a mission in Guatemala is expressed in a letter from a missionary. The first part defines the problem through an exchange of letters between Data International and the missionary. The second part gives a solution suggested by a consultant, and presents a second letter from another missionary in Darjeeling, India who has a similar problem. The third part is an answer from another consultant who uses a different approach to the problem.
  - Data International III, Electrical Appliances, J. W. Hill, 1966; ECL 64; Total 11 pages, with 2 text, 9 exhibits.
    A letter was received by Data International from a missionary going to Urguay raising some interesting questions regarding the use of United States manufactured appliances on both the 60 cycle United States current and the 50 cycle Uruguyan current. Three consultants replied in different ways, providing material for a comparative critical review.
  - Hewlett-Packard V, Microwave Switch, W. E. Bullock, J. W. Hill, G. R. Powley, 1966; ECL 67; Total 27 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 14 text, 13 exhibits.
    In three parts this case briefly summarizes key engineering problems in the development of a high-speed broadband microwave switch. Two main points of focus are concerned with innovations in the design and problems of transferring the design to manufacturing.
  - Ampex Corporation, Tape Recorder Capstan Shaft, K. H. Vesper, J. A. Alic, 1966; ECL 68; Total 44 pages (Parts A,B) with 5 text, 5 exhibits.
    The first part of this short case describes design of a capstan shaft, which must operate smoothly in a precision tape recorder, stopping at the point where bearings must be selected. A second part tells how the engineer on the job designed the bearings and, in particular, how he solved problems of lubrication.
  - City of San Jose-IBM Corporation, Computerized Traffic Control, D. O. Covault, G. A. Fleischer, P. F. Williams, 1966; ECL 69; Total 61 pages (Parts A,B,C,D) with 38 text, 23 exhibits.
    Part A of this case describes how IBM and San Jose try using a digital computer to control city auto traffic. Part B describes the system, C describes strategies with which it was applied, and D gives the results which convinced the city to install a modified system for regular control of certain intersections. Suggestions for the instructor are included.
  - Bechtel Corporation, Process Analysis and Optimization of a Desalting Plant Design, J. W. McCutchan, R. P. Vail, E. N. Ziegler, 1966; ECL 70; Total 39 pages (Parts A,B,C) with 15 text, 24 exhibits.
    Mr. Rufus Crawford in 1964 was asked to help analyze large scale flash distillation of saline water to (1) improve the company's competence in desalting technology and (2) to develop experience in computer aided optimization. The first part presents the problem of deriving a general scheme and criteria for evaluations. The second part poses the problem of developing heat and mass balance equations. A third section describes how Crawford went at the job. An instructor's note is included which suggests assignments and references.
  - Rice in Burma, Arnold, John E. and A. T. Ling, M.I.T., 1952; ECL 1-9; Total 29 pages with 23 text. 6 exhibits. OUT OF PRINT.
    Gives the state-of-the-art in Burmese rice growing. Intended as background from which students can identify design needs as bases for design projects.
  - Chinese Typewriter, Arnold, John E. and A. T. Ling, M.I.T., 1952; ECL 1-11; Total 38 pages with 21 text, 17 exhibits. OUT OF PRINT.
    Tells something about the characters of the Chinese language and about previous ideas for Chinese character typewriters. Intended as a basis for student creative thinking towards better design.
  - Telephone Information Service, Need for a Better Directory System, Arnold, John E., 1959; ECL 1-12; Total 8 pages. OUT OF PRINT.
    Problems of providing telephone numbers quickly and economically to facilitate direct dialing are suggested.
  - Development of an Oil Well Tubing Stripper Rubber, P. E. Bickel, H. O. Fuchs, UCLA, 1964; ECL 1-13; Total 30 pages with 14 text, 16 exhibits.
    Part one is a formal report submitted as evidence of accomplishment in applying for registration as Mechanical Engineer. Part two is an informal tale of adventures recalled on the project.
  - The Wright Brothers' Airplane, H. O. Fuchs, UCLA, 1964; ECL 1-14; Total 29 pages with 14 text, 15 exhibits.
    A history drawn from published sources including quotations of Orville Wright taken from a deposition he gave as a witness in a 1920 lawsuit. Intended for introducing freshmen to engineering design.
  - Design and Development of an Automatic Refrigerator Car Heater, H. O. Fuchs, UCLA, 1963; ECL 1-15; Total 80 pages with 20 text, 60 exhibits.
    History of a product from inception to large-scale use. Told by main customer and chief engineer. Includes samples of engineering reports, patents, drawings, and suggested assignment problems for students.
  - Selected Design Notes, reproduced from the Flight Safety Foundation., ECL 1-16; Total 10 pages.
    A selection of one page illustrated descriptions telling of an aircraft component failure, explaining its cause and the recommended remedy.